how can you transform your trading in
one month I'm talking about making
dramatically more progress in your
trading than you normally would I'm
going to share with you in this video
the exact approach that you need to use
this is the same approach we use with
our members and we've seen some great
results in just the past month or so two
members reached the stage where they're
ready to go for funding other members
transformed their analysis to start
finding great opportunities and one
member who was struggling to find any
trades in their simulator sessions
opened 31 trades and achieved a
56.7% return many of our members praised
the process for helping them to progress
and almost everyone who followed it
correctly saw great benefits now rather
than immediately sharing the plan with
you I want to explain everything in
detail this way you can see that it's
logical evidence-based and effective
like what we try to achieve with
everything here at dwo and hopefully
this means that you will take action
instead of just disregarding it as just
another template I truly believe that
this will add value for you and provide
you with huge benefits when you first
start trading you're constantly learning
new skills techniques Concepts and your
development looks like this but then
over time it begins to flatten out and
eventually it starts to stagnate your
progress just seems to plateau and there
are two common reasons for this you
don't know what you don't know so it
becomes more difficult to try and figure
out exactly what you need to improve or
learn or you stay in your comp comfort
zone often without realizing it you feel
comfortable doing your analysis and
executing trades so you spend your time
doing that instead of continuing your
development what was once purposeful
practice slowly becomes ordinary
practice and as Anders Erikson says
ordinary practice is not enough to reach
Elite levels of performance you need to
constantly push yourself beyond your
abilities and comfort level it feels
frustrating when you stagnate you're
aware your trading isn't at the level
you want it to be and you're not
progressing quickly enough towards that
anymore but most of the time you still
just continue doing what you're doing
and hope your results will eventually
improve but think about what top
football teams do like those in the
Premier League they play one or two
matches per week but they're also
training multiple times per week
studying footage getting insights from
coaches working on their physical
conditioning and much more so imagine
you're a striker who just can't seem to
score would you continue doing what
you're doing and hope for slow
improvement over time unlikely instead
you'd identify the issue spend time
training it getting feedback from
coaches running drills until you get it
right you know people often act as if
trading exists in a bubble and they'll
only look for trading related answers to
their problems but most of the time the
insights that you need can be found
elsewhere like watch this clip with
former Arsenal player Alexander
lacazette talking to the the assistant
coach
benimar top goal
scorer the best the best look at his
movement what's the
Readjustment
oh he gets a little bit lucky but maybe
because of his movement he earns the
luck the only criticism at times lacer
that I could say to you is
that sometimes you're not in the
position to score because you're either
involved in the buildup too much or
you've just been a little bit late or
you've only done one movement
with one movement two movements three
movements in between Center back and
fullback more we can do this more chance
we got to scoring your goals RTI you
should go up because you can finish
that's not the issue and sometimes you
may have to be selfish to be in a
position to score a not link play and
let the number 10 do this you
know okay okay yeah now unfortunately
for us Arsenal fans I think there are
actually many other areas he needs to
improve on really but as you saw in the
clip for lacazette to improve in that
area he has to focus Less on other
things maybe his buildup play will
suffer for a while but it will then lead
to improvements in the area that needs
developing the most over the years I've
seen that this is something that bothers
people when they're learning to trade
they worry that if they neglect certain
areas of their trading to focus on one
area their overall ability will start to
decline so they try to do everything all
the time rather than focusing on the
areas that need it the most and so they
miss out on progress further and faster
you know it's true that when you stop
using or developing a skill you go
through skill Decay but in reality the
amount of skill Decay that you
experience over a short period like 1
month is negligible studies suggest that
complex skills like trading start
deteriorating after more than two months
if not used or practiced frequently and
the more proficient you are with that
skill the slower that decline will be so
the progress you could achieve from one
month of focus on one area would
completely overshadow the sacrifice that
you're making in terms of skill Decay
sometimes you need to take one step back
to take two steps forward so this is
what we challenge our members to do with
the monthly transformation contest that
I mentioned in the last video we thought
of fit like these Fitness
Transformations where you see these
extreme before and after photos how can
we achieve dramatic improvements in a
short space of time well spend one month
hyperfocused on the area of your trading
that either needs it the most or will
have the biggest impact on your overall
development then for us the winner each
month gets a prize like a00 Amazon gift
card or something that will help their
trading and for our quarterly prize
we're paying for someone's funding
application but we don't judge it just
based on the end result like how big the
transformation was it's also judged on
how well planned it was because there's
no point rewarding big successes that
happen by Luck instead if something is
spe specifically planned in a deliberate
realistic and measurable way the process
becomes more predictable and repeatable
think of success like building a house
so your initial development you know the
sort of Rapid progress that you make
right at the start is like setting the
foundations after that it's not about
trying to click your fingers and
magically see a finished house overnight
instead each well-planned monthly
transformation is like stacking one
brick at a time in a dependable way so
let me walk you through exactly how to
do that the transformation plan has
three sections identifying the area of
transformation planning the steps and
reviewing your progress so the first two
sections need to be completed before you
start your month and then the third
section is completed during and at the
end of your month and I recently shared
this template with those of you who have
already gone through our free trading
master class and if you haven't done
that yet I'd really recommend that you
check it out you'll find the link down
below now you should complete this
document with as much detail as possible
and make sure it's written down don't
just keep it in your head there are a
few really important reasons for this
firstly it provides you with a clear
plan to follow each day rather than
anything being left vague or open-ended
so you're more likely to take the right
actions as you progress through the
month secondly it avoids hindsight bias
without setting these things down in
writing it's really easy to get to the
end of the month and believe you
achieved what you set out to even if you
didn't but by writing it specifically
and clearly you can judge your
performance more objectively and make
any changes or improvements for the next
one that you go through which is really
useful thirdly it's been found that
those who write their objectives or
goals in detail are significantly more
likely to achieve them than those who
don't one study found it to be between
1.2 and 1.4 times more likely which is a
big amount and finally by having a
detailed record of all of your
Transformations you can revisit them
from time to time to see how far along
you've come and which approaches led to
the best progress so let's begin with
the first section identifying the
specific area of improvement just like a
smart goal we're making sure that things
are specific achievable relevant and
time bound leaman log who pioneered
smart goals discovered through their
research that elevated performance comes
when five principles are being met
Clarity challenge commitment feedback
and task complexity and they research
spans decades with lots of evidence for
this including one that they did with
lumberjacks where they found that
planning in this way improve performance
and productivity by between 11 and 25%
so we start by identifying the right
area to focus on and the first four
questions that you see there combine to
help you make that decision so together
they're helping you ensure that you're
identifying the right thing because
that's critically important now if
you're not sure where to start with this
try thinking about General problem areas
that you have or maybe aspects that
you've discovered from your trading data
that are holding back your performance
and then from there think logically
about which trading actions or decisions
are contributing to that negative impact
with that underperformance what is it
that you're doing that's leading to that
result what area is it that could be now
if there's more than one area of
improvement which is the case for most
people narrow it down to the one that's
having the biggest negative impact or
that would lead to the biggest overall
benefit if you improved it and in some
cases it's sort of like a lead Domino
that once you solve this one thing it's
going to have a positive knock on effect
in other areas of your trading so if
that's the case you get more bang for
your buck by sort of knocking over that
lead Domino so once you've considered
all four of those questions together
together to help you identify that area
then go ahead and answer each of those
questions in the document so firstly
what specific area are you planning to
focus on for example you might say I
will focus on my trade management then
what led you to choose that area for
improvement and here you want to provide
a detailed reason for that being the
most important area to focus on for this
month for example if it was trade
management you might put once I'm in a
profitable trade I make my decisions
based on gut feeling so by improving my
trade management decisions I can
maximize my opportunities and improve my
returns more than any other change that
I could work on then how is this
currently affecting your trading now if
you have any evidence from your trading
data you can add that in here so for
example you might say I can see in 30%
of my profitable trades I exited too
early and would have achieved much
bigger profits if I stayed in longer 25
% of my losing trades were initially in
a profit greater than two R so if we
have an answer like that we could say
okay great if we work on trade
management is going to improve it but
more importantly where possible you
should provide a vivid description of
how it's affecting your trading
something like I don't feel confident
once I'm in a trade instead I just feel
uncertainty and a lack of clarity I
watch every price tick debating whether
or I should take action once I exit a
trade I feel frustrated when I watch
what the price ends up doing next
remember this process is like a before
and after so by making it Vivid and
detailed you're feeling the pain of the
current situation this helps motivate
you to take action and move away from
that pain and also at the end of the
month it will make things much easier to
recognize the progress that you've made
without being influenced by things like
the peak end rule or other hindsight
related
biases next explain the benefits not
knowing specifically how your trading
will benefit from this transformation
allows you to see that brighter future
that you're moving towards again this
helps with motivation as you're moving
away from that pain that you just
described towards pleasure but this
question also serves as a way of
checking if this is the right
transformation to focus on sure it might
be an area of improvement but are there
other priority areas that could provide
greater benefits so these questions
aren't just for document the
transformation plan they also prompts to
help you to think through these these
different areas and to ensure that
you're identifying the right area of
focus so spend time thinking deeply
about all of these questions before you
commit that plan to writing and go ahead
with that transformation month now you
need to nail down that specific
transformation that you're going to be
working on so you've identified the area
but now what's the specific
transformation and you should word it in
a way that describes the end point so in
other words what you'll be able to do by
the end of this month that you're not
currently doing for example if trade
management is your area of focus well
you're not going to fix everything all
in one month that's not realistic so
what specific transformation can you
make now that will help you get on the
way to achieving that what's the first
brick that you can lay down knowing that
you'll be stacking other bricks one at a
time in future Transformations so in
this case you might focus on scaling out
you've recognized that that some
profitable trades are ending in losses
and some are being closed too early so
if you can learn the right time to scale
out of your positions that will put you
further towards fixing that area so by
the end of this month I'll have Clarity
over when I should partially scale out
from open traes now it's clear you know
what you're trying to achieve in this
month next you need to assess if this is
ambitious enough if it's something that
you're likely to achieve in a regular
month without going through this
transformation process if you could just
achieve by doing what you're already
doing it's not really a transformation
is it you need to be moving in the
challenge skill Zone also known as the
zone of proximal development this is
something we discussed in a previous
video about why trading is so difficult
to learn you can click up there to watch
it basically the gap between your
current level and where you're trying to
get to can't be perceived as being huge
or it becomes demotivating and it leads
to negative emotions like frustration
self-doubt even depression but if it's
not wise enough it can also be
demotivating and it can feel boring if
you want to learn more about this stuff
go and watch that video and it explains
it in more detail a paper by Jonathan
Cohen called the 85% rule for optimal
learning explained that your goals
should be difficult enough that you get
things right 85% of the time and make
mistakes 15% of the time so mistakes
errors they feel frustrating but that
frustration actually engag engages
certain parts of our brain to be more
alert focused and able to learn and this
is one of the key principles of
neuroplasticity now of course it's not
possible to know precisely what will
that 85% level be ahead of time so
instead you just have to use your
initiative with that being a general
Benchmark that you're aiming for and
actually getting the right skill
challenge balance is one of the
prerequisites for achieving a flow State
and getting into flow when you're
learning and developing can give you a
significant Advantage a study by Brain
Monitoring and the US Department of
Defense found that getting a beginner
into a flow State accelerated their
learning meaning that it took 50% less
time than normal to reach an expert
level so if you want to cut down your
development time and get to that expert
level quicker then getting into a flow
state is a good way to do that and
you'll only do that if you get into that
skill challenge sweet spot and finally
for this section the final question
question is is this transformation
realistic to achieve in 4 weeks
obviously if it's not realistic to
achieve in 4 weeks then it's not going
to be a monthly transformation but maybe
it is realistic to achieve in four weeks
but only if you make sacrifices these
might be sacrifices in other areas of
your trading just like that clip that we
watched with Alexander lacazette or
there may be things that you're doing
that take up time like what if you're
going through the financial news each
day looking at the fundamentals and
actually if you cut that out out you
have time to focus on this area
alternatively it may be sacrifices
outside of trading like having less free
time for a month maybe you'll just
sacrifice watching TV in the evenings or
playing games for a certain period of
time just to get this transformation
done and if you do that it's possible to
achieve it in the four weeks so what you
should do is actually detail the
sacrifices that you're willing to make
and therefore you're making that
commitment to yourself okay so now we
get into the nuts and bolts of how you
actually achieve the transformation what
specific steps will you take and how
will you measure your progress because
if something isn't measurable it's much
more difficult to improve on it so the
first thing you need to do is set out
the specific actions you'll take don't
be broad with this instead make the
actions as specific and clear as
possible it doesn't have to be the same
thing every day throughout the whole
month maybe there are several things
that you'll do maybe there's a
progression but make it clear and
specific not only is this another one of
the prerequisites for flow having clear
goals but it also means you're less
likely to procrastinate or be wasteful
during your learning sessions when it's
time to work you'll know exactly what to
do because often it's deciding what to
do that leads people to start
procrastinating getting distracted and
generally wasting their time so for
example if we're looking at that scaling
out transformation that we've been
discussing so far maybe it's like this
week one revisit the Strategic risk
management section in the Duomo program
and complete all purposeful practice
activities week two take all of my
previous trade entries and open them in
a simulator or trading view replay mode
so I can't see what happens next manage
the trades using the scaling out
approaches I learned in week one review
any differences from the original trades
week three go through one month in a
trading simulator enter trades but only
use scaling out for trade management
decisions review how far the decisions
were from optimal week four follow the
same approach from week three but this
time in the live markets with a demo
account now this is just a short example
but the more specific and more detailed
you can be the better it's going to be
for you then throughout the month when
other things come up you'll be able to
see if they fit your plan and if not
maybe Park them until the end of the
transformation month and stay focused
stay on track the next question is there
to Pro want you to think about the
actions in the right way now my advice
is to start with the end in mind so
imagine you've successfully achieved the
transformation and then work backwards
from there so what would the final
actions be what about the ones before
those and before those and so on that's
a great way to think about things like
this then and this is so important how
will you measure your progress and it's
important that you choose something
that's specific to the area you're
trying to focus on you shouldn't use an
over over all measure like returns for
example because that's too broad and you
won't be able to tell if improvements
are from that specific area you're
trying to improve on and also it depends
too much on the markets themselves which
aren't in your control so you need to
find something specific to the area
you're working on and you know it can be
difficult sometimes to find the ideal
measure to focus on but if you're
struggling just try approaching it from
different angles don't get sort of
trapped by looking at the standard
trading data and thinking what can I use
think differently about it maybe even
use different measures for the different
tasks that you're doing throughout the
month so for example week one might be
about the percentage completed of the
lessons and activities this sort of
stuff you want to get through you know
that's 100% so what percentage are you
completing each day then on one
particular day if you're under the
percentage you need to go to to reach to
complete this in a week the next day you
know you need to do more and so on and
so on week two might focus on how much
better the performance is on your trades
now having sort of Revisited the scaling
out parts of the the program compared to
the original trades that you took so
there's a comparison there you can see
the difference between the performance
week three and week four might be a
measure showing how far you were from
optimal or as we'll discuss in a moment
it might be about how many mistakes are
pointed out to you when you go to get
feedback in the community now depending
on which area you're focusing on you may
also want to consider the pairing
principle this was made Popular by Andy
Grove in his book higher output
management and he says measures tend to
direct your attention towards what
they're monitoring it's like riding a
bicycle you'll probably steer it where
you are looking then as Mark Andre
points out the problem with arbitrary
metrics in complex situations they tend
to backfire give emergency services
drivers rigid response time metrics and
they'll tend to stay close to Urban
centers the solution is that every
measure should have a paired measure
that's addressing the possible negative
consequences of the first measure I'll
give you an example because that's a bit
of a tricky one to get your head around
when you first hear it so for someone
wanting to open more trades if they
measure the number of Trades that they
open it's just going to encourage them
to open low quality ones they're not
saying the quality of the trade there
they're just saying open more trades so
instead they need to pair quantity with
another measure that avoids the negative
consequences so for example maybe it's
number of Trades with a positive
expectancy that's then looking at the
thing they want to improve and something
that's maintaining the quality so they
don't have the negative consequences the
next question was more relevant for our
members because that's who this was
originally for they have access to our
community they can get instant feedback
but if you don't have something like
that think about how you can keep
yourself accountable and it's even
better if you can build this into your
planned actions and therefore create
some sort of flywheel effect and if
you're not sure about that then uh check
out this video up here where we talks
about the flywheel effect in relation to
your trading so in this case it might be
something like complete a trade get
feedback in the community assess and
implement the feedback complete another
trade get feedback and so on and so on
flywheel goes round and round then
importantly and this is something a lot
of people don't consider how will you
know that you've achieved the
transformation what measure will you
have achieved to know that it's
completed what's that trigger point this
should align with your description of
the successful transformation from the
first section of the plan but if not
then you either need to change the
actions that you're planning or reassess
the intended transformation by making
this clear and measurable it will help
you track how far you are from achieving
it as you progress through the month and
this also Taps into your intrinsic
drivers to help you push yourself even
more to achieve more than you would in a
regular month so you don't want
something vague or that leaves things
open to interpretation or makes you
unsure at the end of the month if you've
even actually succeeded or not you know
there are three main reasons that people
don't achieve their goals they don't
take the actions they were meant to take
they were unrealistic with the goal they
were trying to achieve or other things
happened that got in the way now what
we've gone through so far deals with
those first two points the final
question in this section deals with the
third one think through all the things
that may go wrong and then find a way to
mitigate those risks or have a
contingency plan know how you're going
to deal with them now I'd recommend
going through a premortem analysis this
is something that was developed by the
psychologist Gary Klein basically a
postmortem analysis happens at the end
of something to assess what happened but
a premortal analysis is done before you
even start so you imagine you're at the
end and you failed then brainstorm all
the possible things that could have led
to that failure now you know all the
things that could go wrong so you can
have a plan for them now don't just
think about trading related issues also
think through the personal side and even
the influence of other people people
sort of interfering and sort of swaying
your decisions or getting you to go and
do other things think about all of that
now one of our members did an amazing
job with this they set out processes or
protocols to follow when certain
situations occur that might affect them
negatively so for example since failure
is just an inevitable part of learning
they knew that there'd be some L's along
the way which may change their mindset
so they already planned exactly how they
get their minds back on track in those
inevitable moments okay so everything
that we've been through so far is what
you need to do before you start the
transformation month and now we get to
the final section which is to be
completed during the transformation
month with a final review that happens
at the end of the transformation month I
think all of it's quite self-explanatory
so we'll go through this bit quite
quickly I'll give give you a brief
overview but I know it's tempting to
skip this part of the process a lot of
people don't like doing the review part
at the end but it's really important
self-reflection and self-correction have
been shown to be a really important part
of a development process and actually
contribute to accelerated learning so
don't skip over this bit so the weekly
reviews are a chance to think about what
went well and what you maybe need to
adjust to make the next week even better
you can set yourself action items of
things that you need to focus on for the
next week so it's just a chance to
continue to course correct so you have
the best opportunity to achieve the
transformation and it's important that
you're brutally honest with yourself
about whether you actually did the
actions that you're meant to and whether
you're progressing in the way that you
need to to achieve the transformation
with things like this I always remind
myself about Solomon's Paradox which we
actually discussed in a video a while
ago which was all about overcoming
negative selft talk in trading we'll
link it up there so it's a cognitive
bias that we have where we give
difference and usually better advice to
other people than we do for ourselves so
a good way to sort of make use of this
is to try and imagine yourself as a
third party reviewing what you've done
or imagine that you're giving feedback
to someone else so what would you say to
improve the chances of that person
staying on course and completing the
transformation how can you be critical
and pick up on the things that they need
to do better and then at the end you do
a final review and again be brutally
honest with with yourself about whether
you did the actions that you were meant
to do whether you got distracted or
sidetracked and whether you genuinely
achieved the transformation or not you
know it's only by being honest with
yourself here that you can actually
provide answers to the final two
questions that will actually be useful
to you you see by documenting this in
detail each time you go through a
transformation month your
Transformations will continue to get
better and better most people are over
or under ambitious for the first one but
by going through this process the whole
process you'll tighten up the next one
and the next one and the next you'll
take on that feedback and eventually
you'll find that sweet spot where your
plans are reliable and the outcomes
therefore are more predictable so once
you complete this transformation take on
the feedback that you've given yourself
or that you've got from me or the
community if you're one of our members
and start planning the next one each
month Brick by Brick you'll be
constructing the trader that you want to
be you're Paving a dependable path
towards your long-term goals no more
trying to do everything all at once and
hoping for the best just like everything
we do here we've try to make this as
logical and evidence-based as possible
so I hope you found this useful and if
you have please hit the like button and
I hope you'll take on board everything
you've learned in this session to start
creating that more reliable path for
yourself and if you're planning to do
that leave a comment below make a
commitment and let me know what you'll
be doing thanks a lot for watching I'll
see you in the next one one take care